<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_jtei.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="jTEI">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">Encoding GeoJSON Geometries in TEI</title>

            <author>
               <name xml:id="mholmes">
                  <forename>Martin</forename>
                  <surname>Holmes</surname>
               </name>
               <affiliation>University of Victoria Humanities Computing and Media
                  Centre</affiliation>
               <email>mholmes@uvic.ca</email>
            </author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher>
            <date/>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <p>For this publication a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license
                     has been granted by the author(s) who retain full copyright.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>No source, born digital. Abstract for submission to the TEI 2018 Conference in
               Tokyo.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The BreezeMap project is developing a code-base for integrating GeoJSON, OpenLayers,
               and TEI for constructing maps, facsimiles, and gazetteers using TEI.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">en</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords xml:lang="en">
               <term>maps</term>
               <term>GeoJSON</term>
               <term>facsimiles</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#mholmes" when="2018-03-29">Created this document…</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="abstract" xml:id="abstract">
            <p>This presentation will address two distinct but related issues concerning the
            representation of feature geometries on two-dimensional surfaces in TEI.</p>
            
            <p>Over the last decade, GeoJSON has proved itself as a simple, efficient and rich standard for 
            encoding map features, and is widely used throughout the GIS community, eclipsing
            other apparently more XML-friendly options such as GML and KML. As more TEI projects
            incorporate GIS data, there is a need to provide examples of good practice which 
            enable the integration of GeoJSON-encoded feature geometries (Point, LineString, Polygon,
            MultiPoint, MultiLineString, MultiPolygon and MultiGeometry) with TEI encoding.
            The first half of this presentation will show how the University of Victoria’s
            BreezeMap project is approaching this problem.</p>
            
            <p>The second half of the presentation will address the need to encode 
            similar complex geometries inside the TEI <gi>facsimile</gi> element, to represent
            points, lines and polygons on text-bearing surfaces or other two-dimensional 
            coordinate spaces. The model of GeoJSON can be helpful here too, and although
            the existing TEI element-set (<gi>surface</gi>, <gi>zone</gi>, and the soon-to-be-added
            <gi>path</gi>), along with their current attribute array, already make this possible,
            there are many possible approaches that might be taken for any given geometry. It would
            be desirable to settle on a set of best practices and exemplify them in the TEI
            Guidelines.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>

         <div xml:id="geojson">
            <head>GeoJSON and BreezeMap</head>
            <p> Although the GeoJSON format was both stable and widely supported by 2008, it was not
               until 2016 that the Internet Engineering Task Force adopted it, with some minor
               changes, as an RFC (<ref target="#ietf2016" type="bibl">IETF 2016</ref>). Software
               support for GeoJSON is now virtually universal in the mapping community. </p>

            <p>GeoJSON provides a clear and easily-processable array of feature geometries,
               including primitives (Point, LineString, Polygon) and complex combinations
               (MultiPoint, MultiLineString, MultiPolygon and MultiGeometry) to enable the encoding
               of locations (features) on a mapping surface using GIS coordinates.</p>

            <p>Our <ref target="https://github.com/martindholmes/BreezeMap">BreezeMap</ref> project
               aims to create a toolset based on <ref target="http://openlayers.org"
                  >OpenLayers</ref>, GeoJSON and TEI for creating interactive maps and
               gazetteers, as well as an approach for encoding complex features on textual 
            facsimiles and other surfaces represented as two-dimensional digital images. This
            presentation will discuss the approaches taken to integrating
            TEI and GeoJSON in the BreezeMap project.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="mapping">
            <head>Mapping in TEI</head>
            <p>Projects marrying TEI and GIS are increasingly common (<ref type="bibl"
                  target="#hickcox2013">Hickcox et al 2013</ref>, <ref type="bibl"
                  target="#jenstad2006">Jenstad 2006-present</ref>). The TEI treats places as
               first-order entities, and building a gazetteer using <gi>listPlace</gi> and
                  <gi>place</gi> is straightforward, but support for actual GIS is currently very
               limited (see my TEI feature request <ref
                  target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1474">Need to improve GIS/gazetteer
                  encoding support in TEI</ref>). The TEI <gi>geo</gi> element <quote
                  source="#teiref1">contains any expression of a set of geographic coordinates,
                  representing a point, line, or area on the surface of the earth in some
                  notation.</quote> (<ref xml:id="teiref1" target="#tei2018" type="bibl">TEI
                  2018</ref>), a rather vague definition which is currently supplemented by only a
               few examples showing single points encoded as a simple coordinate pair, or embedded
               GML showing a Linear Ring. For encoders who would like to make use of the range of
               geometries available in modern mapping standards, it would help to have a few clear
               examples showing GeoJSON embedded in TEI, as in <ref type="crossref" target="#exampleGeo">Example 1</ref>, 
               which is taken from a campus map that forms one of the test projects in BreezeMap: 
               
               <figure xml:id="exampleGeo">
                  
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <place xml:id="bldgElliottTheatre" corresp="#bldgTeaching">
                        <placeName>Elliott Lecture Theatre</placeName>
                        <desc>...</desc>
                        <location type="GeoJSON">
                           <geo crs="urn:ogc:def:crs:OGC:1.3:CRS84"
                              geoEncoding="GeoJSON">"geometry":{"type":"Polygon",
                              "coordinates":[[[-123.3108016,48.4627526],[-123.3102577,48.4627937],[-123.3102336,48.4626537],[-123.3102028,48.4624747],[-123.3107466,48.4624335],[-123.310778,48.4626155],[-123.3108016,48.4627526]]]}</geo>
                        </location>
                     </place>
                  </egXML>
                  <head type="legend">A TEI <gi>place</gi> element incorporating GeoJSON
                     geometry</head>
               </figure>
               
               The <att>crs</att> and <att>geoEncoding</att> attributes, which are part of
               the feature request mentioned above, will
               provide better options for machine-readable encoding than the current <gi>geoDecl</gi>
               header element allows. The actual feature geometry is expressed in its pure GeoJSON 
               format, and is easily machine-readable. Converting a TEI gazetteer constructed like 
               this into a GeoJSON file for display in a mapping application is trivial, especially
               with XSLT 3.0's enhanced support for JSON.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="facsimiles">
            <head>Facsimiles</head>
            <p>The GeoJSON RFC specifies that <quote source="#ietfref1">GeoJSON uses a geographic coordinate
                  reference system, World Geodetic System 1984, and units of decimal
                  degrees.</quote>, and <quote source="#ietfref1">the first two elements [of a
                  position] are longitude and latitude, or easting and northing</quote>, (<ref
                  xml:id="ietfref1" target="#ietf2016" type="bibl">IETF 2016</ref>); in other words,
               it is intended only for geographic data. However, there is nothing intrinsic to the
               specification of geometries in the RFC which precludes using the same structures
               to describe features on any two- or three-dimensional surface. The same types of
               feature (points, lines, polygons, and combinations of them) are a natural fit when
               annotating manuscript images, engravings, and other pictorial or textual content in
               any TEI project which incorporates a facsimile component. A mapping library such as
               OpenLayers will happily display any static image with features described in
                  <soCalled>GeoJSON</soCalled> which actually consist only of pixel offsets. 
               This is the approach we take when encoding pseudo-geographical coordinates on 
               historical maps which are not, or cannot be, geo-rectified, as in the case of the 
               Agas Map (<ref type="bibl" target="#jenstad2015">Jenstad et al. 2015</ref>).
               
               <figure xml:id="agas">
                  <graphic url="images/agas.png" width="867px" height="711px"/>
                  <head type="legend">A detail from the Agas Map, which shows features
                  outlines using polygons and lines which are expressed in GeoJSON in 
                  the TEI encoding</head>
               </figure>
            </p>

            <p>This makes <soCalled>GeoJSON</soCalled> (or at least, its formal structure)
               a natural fit for rendering annotated images,
               and interfaces such as those provided by OpenLayers drawing tools a good option for
                  <soCalled>authoring</soCalled> such features. The question then is how best to
               encode the resulting data, in a non-lossy manner, in the existing TEI elements for
               describing features on a surface (<gi>zone</gi> and the soon-to-be-available
                  <gi>path</gi>). Browser-based drawing tools developed and optimized for maps
               can now provide a more powerful alternative to older, less sophisticated tools for
               facsimile editing, such as my own Image Markup Tool (<ref type="bibl" target="#holmes2012">Holmes 2012</ref>).
            </p>
               
               <p>The remainder of this presentation will examine ways in which such
               geometries can be encoded in TEI, and easily recovered into GeoJSON structures for
               rendering purposes. </p>
         </div>
      </body>

      <back>
         <div type="bibliography">

            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="hickcox2013"><author>Hickcox, Alice</author>, <author>Michael C.
                     Page</author>, and <author>Randy Gue</author>. <date>2013</date>. <title
                     level="a">The Atlanta Map project: TEI and GIS collaborate to create a research
                     environment</title>. Digital Humanities 2013 Conference, Nebraska. <ref
                     target="http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-416.html"
                     >http://dh2013.unl.edu/abstracts/ab-416.html</ref>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="holmes2012"><author>Holmes, Martin</author>. <date>2012</date>. <title
                     level="m">Image Markup Tool</title>. Version 1.8.2.2. <ref
                     target="https://hcmc.uvic.ca/~mholmes/image_markup/"
                     >https://hcmc.uvic.ca/~mholmes/image_markup/</ref>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="ietf2016"><author>Internet Engineering Task Force</author>.
                     <date>2016</date>. <title level="m">The GeoJSON Format</title>. <idno>Request
                     for Comments (RFC) No. 7946</idno>. <ref
                     target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7946"
                     >https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7946</ref>.</bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="jenstad2015"><author>Jenstad, Janelle</author>, <author>Kim
                     McLean-Fiander</author>, <author>Greg Newton</author> and <author>Martin
                     Holmes</author>. <date>2015</date>. <title level="a">How To Edit a Map in
                     TEI</title>. Digital Humanities 2015 Conference, Sydney, Australia. <ref
                     target="http://dh2015.org/abstracts/xml/JENSTAD_Janelle_Auriol_How_To_Edit_a_Map_in_TEI//JENSTAD_Janelle_Auriol_How_To_Edit_a_Map_in_TEI.html"
                     >http://dh2015.org/abstracts/xml/JENSTAD_Janelle_Auriol_How_To_Edit_a_Map_in_TEI//JENSTAD_Janelle_Auriol_How_To_Edit_a_Map_in_TEI.html</ref>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="jenstad2006"><editor>Jenstad, Janelle</editor>.
                     <date>2006-present</date>. The Map of Early Modern London. <ref
                     target="http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/">http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/</ref></bibl>

               <bibl xml:id="tei2018"><author>TEI Consortium</author>. <date>2018</date>. <title
                     level="m">TEI Guidelines</title>, version <ref
                     target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.3.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"
                     >3.3.0</ref>. </bibl>

            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
